Guide to the George Alexander Kubler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Alexander Kubler papers
1872-2000
MS 843
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
104.5
(108 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, research materials, and writings documenting the academic career of George Kubler, and correspondence and records from his service as chief of the UNESCO mission to Cuzco, Peru, following the earthquake in that city on May 20, 1951.
Kubler, George, 1912-1996
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 1997-M-022, boxes 2, 7, 10, 32, 32A, 36-38, 41-42, 46, and 49-51 are open for research. The rest of the material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George Kubler, 1987, 1995-1996. Gift of Elizabeth Kubler, 1997-2002. Transfer from the Art and Architecture Library, 1998, 2005. Transfer from Research Services and Collections, 1999. Transfer from History of Art Department, 2008, 2011.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of plans, reports, and memoranda from George Alexander Kubler's service as chief of the UNESCO mission to Cuzco, Peru, following the earthquake in that city on May 20, 1951. The largest portion of the papers is made up of reports of the Junta de Reconstrucción y Fomento Industrial del Cuzco, 1952-1956, with supporting charts and tables of costs. There are also a pilot plan issued in 1951 by the Oficina Nacional de Planeamiento y Urbanismo and recommendations for the preservation of cultural monuments (1955). Writings by Kubler include a speech on the work of the Junta (1955), and miscellaneous notes, in particular a group entitled "Pilot Plan, 1955". Almost all of the papers, other than Kubler's notes, are in Spanish.
Biographical / Historical
George A. Kubler was a noted professor of art history at Yale University from 1938 until his retirement. He was chief of the UNESCO Mission to Cuzco, Peru in 1951; and a Guggenheim fellow in Mexico, 1943-1944, and in Spain, 1952-1953. Kubler was a member of numerous learned societies and author of books and articles. He died on October 3, 1996.
Art -- History; City planning -- Peru; Earthquakes -- Peru; Cuzco (Peru); Peru; Art historians; Kubler, George, 1912-1996; Yale University. School of Art
- Original accession, [1950?]-1958; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Reports, plans, and memoranda
    - Cuzco - Lesiones en los Edificios - Recomendaciones para su Reparación, [1950?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Junta de Reconstrucción y Fomento Industrial del Cuzco
      - Costs of reconstruction in charts and tables, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Report, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - "Memoria Anual", 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Memorandum sobre el Problema de Energía e Industrialización de la Ciudad del Cuzco y Zonas de Influencia en el Departamento, 1956 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Kubler, George: "Pilot Plan"; speech; notes, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Marchese, Pietro: "Memorandum en Favor del Arte y la Cultura Peruana", 1955 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Oficina Nacional de Planeamiento y Urbanismo
      - "Plan Pilota del Cuzco", 1951 August (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Planeamiento General", 1952 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Toma de Contacto con el Cusco", 1952 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional material, Accession 1988-M-004; 5.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Inventory by Joseph P. Papagoda, 1987 Nov
  Received from: George Kubler, 1987 Jul 7
  - Correspondence
    - A - C, 1938-1983 (Box 1)
    - D - H, 1938-1983 (Box 2)
    - Harvard, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - I - M, 1938-1983 (Box 3)
    - N - R, 1938-1983 (Box 4)
    - S - Z, 1938-1983 (Box 5)
    - Italy-Madrid, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
    - Lisbon, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Fulbright Research Fellow, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
- Additional material, 1988-1991; Accession 1996-M-089; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Esthetic Recognition of Ancient Amerindian Art [drafts, typescripts, page proofs, research material], 1988-1991 (Box 1–2)
  - Smith College Lectures, 1990 (Box 2)
- Additional material, Accession 1997-M-022; 50.5 linear feet (51 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 2, 4, 7, 10, 32, 32A, 36-38, 41-42, 46, and 49-51 are open for research. The rest of the boxes are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Graduate student correspondence, 1970-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence [professional], mostly, 1984-1994
    - A - R (Box 2)
    - S - Z (Box 3)
  - Writings [mostly manuscripts and drafts]
    - The Shape of Time [manuscript and drafts] (10 folders) (Box 4)
    - Ancient American Art and Architecture [manuscript] (8 folders) (Box 4)
    - Building the Escorial [manuscript] (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - Studies in Classic Maya Iconography [manuscript] (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Art and Architecture in Spain and Portugal their American Dominions, 1500-1800
      - Page proof (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Handwritten draft (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Typed draft #1 (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Typed draft #2 (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Esthetic Recognition of Ancient Amerindian Art (91 folders) (Box 5–6)
  - Miscellaneous files (33 folders) (Box 7)
  - Card files (Box 8)
    - Esthetic Recognition of Ancient Amerindian Art [bibliography] (Box 8)
    - Spain and Felix da Costa (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, photographs, prints, slides relating to establishing the provenance of various art objects (Box 9)
  - Notes [typed index cards and postcards] (Box 9)
  - Maya glyphs [photographs, printed material, correspondence] (Box 9)
  - Santa Clara monastery [Colombia] (Box 9)
  - Lectures [notes and handouts on Maya] (Box 9)
  - Kubler ERAAA [correspondence, drafts, encyclopedia entry], 1990 (Box 9)
  - Period, Style and Meaning in Ancient American Art (Box 9)
  - HASSA
    - Exams, grades, 1979 (Box 9)
    - Class files, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Book files [Chapters 1-15] (Box 9)
  - Class files for different years [syllabi, lecture notes, grades: arranged by year] (Box 10)
  - Lectures [arranged by title] (Box 10)
  - "Andalusia" [chapter of a book] (Box 10)
  - Religious Art of New Mexico
    - Files on publication; drafts of chapters (Box 10)
    - Copy of book; other book on topic (Box 11)
  - Southwestern Research Mission Center (Box 11)
  - Book [typed drafts] (Box 11)
  - Student papers and correspondence (Box 11)
  - Student papers and grant proposals (Box 11)
  - Escorial files [notebooks; card files; unidentified slides, canisters of film] (Box 12–17)
  - Portugal files (Box 18–19)
  - Portugal photograph album; Maya sites and notes (Box 20)
  - Maya notes (Box 21–23)
  - Tikal
    - General information [Correspondence, bibliography, reports, manuscript photographs] (Box 24–25)
    - Photographs, monuments, inscriptions (Box 26–28)
  - Burrus microfilms, photographic negatives (Box 29)
  - Europe [reprints, correspondence, notes]
    - A - E (Box 30)
    - F - L (Box 31)
    - M - R (Box 32)
    - S (Box 32A)
    - S - Z (Box 33)
  - Latin America [reprints, correspondence, notes]
    - A - B (Box 33)
    - C - M (Box 34)
    - N - Z (Box 35)
  - Research materials (Box 36–38)
    Contains correspondence, unpublished papers, notes, articles, bibliographies: relating to a wide range of topics in anthropology, archeology, art history. Box 38 contains microfilm of Colonial manuscripts; microfilm of European books; and European travel photographs and negatives: Portugal, Spain, Italy (1952-1964).
  - Dumbarton Oaks; LCB Library [Providence, Rhode Island] (Box 39)
  - LCB Library [Providence, Rhode Island]; seminars, talks, and conferences files; writings by others (Box 40)
  - Seminars, talks, and conferences files; writings by others (Box 41–43)
  - Maya research files; lectures and notes; slides (Box 44)
    Glass slides must be used by appointment.
  - Research files (Box 45)
  - Writings by others (Box 46)
  - Building the Escorial [manuscript] (Box 47)
  - Office files [correspondence and research materials in alphabetical file folders; photographs] (Box 48)
  - Writings and personal files (Box 49–51)
- Additional material, Accession 1997-M-146; 4 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Classic Maya Seminar, 1968 (Box 1–2)
  - Photographs (Box 3–4)
- Additional material, Accession 1998-M-082; 5 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Writings; subject files; student papers, 1940s-1980s (Box 1–5)
- Additional material, Accession 1998-M-102; 1; (1 box)
  - Writings; correspondence; student papers; collected materials on Mexican and New Mexico art, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 1)
- Additional material, Accession 1998-M-103; 5 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Writings, including Shape of Time; working papers; conferences; teaching files, 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 1)
  - Student files; writings, including Art and Architecture in America and Shape of Time, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Card files, bibliographic and notes; symposia; student files; writing files, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 3)
  - Pre-Columbian art in Olsen collection, Yale Art Gallery, 1970s-1980s (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous; Shape of Time; articles, 1930s-1940s, 1980s (Box 5)
- Additional material, Accession 1999-M-032; 10 linear feet (10 boxes)
  - Building the Escorial [manuscript], 1981 (Box 1)
  - Symposia and meetings, 1964-1984 (Box 2)
  - Teaching materials, 1940s-1980s (Box 3)
  - Teaching materials; lectures; papers, 1960s (Box 4)
  - Writings; miscellaneous [unsorted], 1960s, undated (Box 5)
  - Articles; conferences, 1950s-1980s (Box 6)
  - "Tikal" project; Art Hispanial [manuscript]; William Hickling Prescott [manuscript], undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph files (3" x 5"); card files; microfilm, undated (Box 8–9)
  - "Photos Mexico XVI" [mostly 3" x 5," 5" x 7"], undated (Box 10)
- Additional material, Accession 1999-M-044; 3 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - NYU course notes, 1930s; talks, lectures, articles, 1960s-1980s, undated (Box 1)
  - Subject files, no date; teaching files, 1960s, no date; lectures, 1960s, undated (Box 2)
  - NYU class notes, 1930s; lectures, 1960s, no date; subject files, undated (Box 3)
- Additional material, Accession 1999-M-107; 4 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Writings (by Kubler and others), 1960s, 1970s, 1980s (Box 1)
  - Photographs and Research Notes, Portugal and Spain, 1928, 1950s, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, Portugal and Spain, 1978, undated (Box 3)
  - Writings on Spain, Research Notes on Portugal, undated (Box 4)
- Additional material, Accession 1999-M-108; 4 linear feet (4 boxes)
  - Writings, 1930s, 1940s, undated (Box 1)
  - Writings, research notes, 1970s, 1980s, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1940s, undated (Box 3)
  - Writings, research files, 1940s, 1970s, n.d (Box 4)
- Additional material, Accession 2000-M-056; 3 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Writings, research files, 1940s-1970s (Box 1–3)
- Additional material, Accession 2000-M-104; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Dark, Philip J.C., 1953-1957, undated (Box 1)
    - Hays, Daniel, undated (Box 1)
    - Portuguese ivories, 1943-1950 (Box 1)
    - Tovar manuscript, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
    - Tschall, Peter, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and maps
    - D'Andrade, A. Galvram, undated (Box 1)
    - De Herrera, Antonio, undated (Box 1)
    - Ixcquixtla, undated (Box 1)
    - Portuguese ivories, undated (Box 1)
    - Santa Cruz, undated (Box 1)
    - Stendall manuscripts, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Subject files
    - Albers traveling fellowship, 1975-1983 (Box 1)
    - Architecture in Latin America [colonial], undated (Box 1)
    - Aztec conference, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Burgoa and others, undated (Box 1)
    - Careri, Cremelli, undated (Box 1)
    - Carmago, Munoz, 1948, undated (Box 1)
    - Chavero, undated (Box 1)
    - Clavigero, undated (Box 1)
    - Codex and codices, 1947-1980, undated (Box 1)
    - Cuauhtinchan, 1927 (Box 1)
    - de Costa, 1962, 1999, undated (Box 1)
    - De la Arena, Mauricio, undated (Box 1)
    - Del Castillo, Cristóbal, 1908, undated (Box 1)
    - De León, Martin, undated (Box 1)
    - De Salazar, Cervantes, undated (Box 1)
    - Durán, Diego, 1964, undated (Box 1)
    - Fuenleal, C., 1969, 1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Garcia, Gregoria, undated (Box 1)
    - Glass, John B., 1957-1975 (Box 1)
    - Hazard Fund, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Hernández, Francisco, undated (Box 1)
    - Huango, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Humboldt manuscript #1, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Kalandairo Mexicano, 1948, undated (Box 1)
    - Kingsborough, 1954-1957, undated (Box 1)
    - Landa calendar, 1948, undated (Box 1)
    - Las casas, undated (Box 1)
    - Lists of officers in America, undated (Box 1)
    - López, Ruiz, 1966, undated (Box 1)
    - Mexican Indian pictorial documents, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Mexico, 1955-1961 (Box 2)
    - Mixtec archaeology, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Mixtec bibliography, undated (Box 2)
    - Motoliria, 1903, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes on Mexican site visits, undated (Box 2)
    - Serna, undated (Box 2)
    - Seville [archive], 1953, undated (Box 2)
    - Shepherd-Rockery, 1931-1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Sigüenza, Mapade, 1951, 1977, undated (Box 2)
    - Techialoyan group, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Theut, A., 1961-1977 (Box 2)
    - Tlaxcala, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Tolteca, undated (Box 2)
    - Tovar calendar, 1872-1879, 1947-1948, undated (Box 2)
    - Urbanism, sixteenth century, undated (Box 2)
    - Wilder, Mitchell, 1962-1964, undated (Box 2)
    - Yale University [History of Art 55, class outline and lecture notes], 1950-1956, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous publications of others, 1955-1969 (Box 2)
- Additional material, Accession 2002-M-056; 2 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Publication style sheets, undated (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies and outlines for History of Art 12, undated (Box 1)
  - History of Art 85B, undated (Box 1)
  - George Washington, undated (Box 1)
  - Peterson, Charles E. [correspondence], 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Perspecta, 1970 1970 (Box 1)
  - Freshman history - Versailles, undated (Box 1)
  - University of Chicago, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Kansas, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Foreign area survey, 1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Jaguars in Mexico, 1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Seventeenth century eastern seaboard, undated (Box 1)
  - Art 42, 1943, 1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Teotihuacán, undated (Box 1)
  - R E Glyph, undated (Box 1)
  - History of Art department, 1945-1947, undated (Box 1)
  - Seventeenth century, undated (Box 1)
  - Eighteenth century, undated (Box 1)
  - Mazapán, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
  - Georgia missions, 1948, undated (Box 1)
  - Early republican period, undated (Box 1)
  - Text figures, 1999, undated (Box 1)
  - First Inter-American Conference on Philosophy, 1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Dumbarton Oaks, 1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Worcester Art Museum, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Craftsmanship, undated (Box 1)
  - Reprints, mailing lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Art Bulletin index, 1948-1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Oaxaca railroad map, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Focillon excerpts, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Book purchase recommendations, 1945-1946, undated (Box 1)
  - "Aspects of Latin American Art" [lecture], 1943 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
  - Caroll Meeks' memorial service, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Clancy, Flora [dissertation], 1980 (Box 2)
  - Prints and negatives, undated (Box 2)
  - San Marcos microfilm account, 1951, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1955-1999 (Box 2)
  - Annual meeting of the Association of the John Carter Brown Library, 1947-1951, undated (Box 2)
  - Seventeenth century, undated (Box 2)
  - Tovar Calendar, 1950-1952, undated (Box 2)
  - Indian shepherds, 1947-1971 (Box 2)
  - Sacred Heart, undated (Box 2)
  - List of books on Latin America, undated (Box 2)
  - History of Art 55a, 55b, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Penguin Books, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Reese, Tom?, undated (Box 2)
  - Castas, undated (Box 2)
  - History of Art 255b, 1968, undated (Box 2)
  - Mexican urbanism, 1955, undated (Box 2)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1965-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - Mexico, eighteenth century architects, 1960, undated (Box 2)
  - Art 53, 1940, 1947, undated (Box 2)
  - Jorge Olvera, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Mexico, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Codex files, 1940s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Creighton University, 1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Oronica Mexicayotl, undated (Box 2)
  - Costumbros de 1553, Escorial, undated (Box 2)
- Additional material, Accession 2005-M-094; 1
  - Research materials on Spain [notes, printed materials, and photographs; 7 binders], Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1944-1998; Accession 2009-M-014; 1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Biographical material on Kubler, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Speculum, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Archeological file, Circa 1946-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Additional material, Circa 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Archeological file, correspondence, and printed ephemera, Circa 1950-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7-15)
  - Book on early Mexican art, draft, Circa 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Conference materials, XXXV Congreso Internacional de Americanistas, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bustios Galves, Luis, "Preambulo", typescript, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reviews and notes, Circa 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Robinson, Donald and Martha, photographs and memorial service ephemera, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Coggins, Clemency, The Shapes of Time at Tikal, for a workshop with George Kubler on visual imagery, 1981 April 24 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings and notes, Circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings, book introduction, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs
    - Kubler, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Palacio Nacional, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, 1953-1957; Accession 2011-M-089
  - Correspondence
    - L, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - M, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mac, Mc, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - N, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - O, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - P, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Q, Circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - R, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Reviews, articles, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - S, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - T, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - V, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - W, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)